A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Overseas Development, International Training and Research, Administrative Files FA587
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Overseas Development, International Training and Research, Administrative Files
1951-1967
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA587
9.55 Cubic Feet 7 record storage boxes, 1 letter document box.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
As received.
Scope and Contents
Includes but not limited to: correspondence, reports, program and division memoranda, documentation of program planning, training and researh, program consultants, office procedures, and procedural manuals.
- Chronological Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 1)
  - Area One Notebook -- Dyke Brown, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Jan 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Feb 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Mar 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Apr 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, May 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Jun 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Jul 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Aug 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Sep 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Oct 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Nov 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Dec 1952 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Jan 1953 (Box 1)
  - Chron File, Feb 1953 (Box 1)
- Master Set -- Docket Items, 1954-1966 (Box 2)
  - ITR Docket Items and Grant Requests, 1954-1957 (Box 2)
  - ITR Docket Items and Grant Requests, 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - ITR Docket Items and Grant Requests, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
  - Docket Items -- Fiscal, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Docket Items -- Fiscal, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Docket Items -- Fiscal (1/2), 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Docket Items -- Fiscal (2/2), 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Master Set -- International Legal Studies -- Docket Items and Grant Requests, 1966 (Box 2)
- Annual Reports -- General File re: Drafts--Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
- Correspondence and Records Control -- Instructions, 1957-1966 (Box 3)
- Memoranda to McGeorge Bundy from John B Howard (Box 3)
- International Programs 1954 Reorganization (Box 3)
- International Programs 1957 Reorganization (Box 3)
- International Programs General File, 1960-1962 (Box 3)
- Research and Training -- China, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
- Research and Training -- Africa, 1954-1958 (Box 3)
- Exchange of Persons, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
- Training and Research Programs, 1954-1965 (Box 3)
- Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR), 1952-1958 (Box 3)
- Training and Research -- Japan, 1957 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- International Legal Studies, 1955-1957 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- USSR, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
- National Defense Education Act, 1958 (Box 3)
- Fellowship Programs, 1954-1958 (Box 3)
- Division of Overseas Activities (DOA) -- Staff Meetings, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- Staff Meetings -- Reports, 1955-1961 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- General Correspondence -- Miscellaneous, 1952-1958 (Box 3)
- Division of Overseas Activities -- Project Control -- Records, Feb 1954 (Box 3)
- Office Procedures -- 1960 and Prior Years, 1952-1960 (Box 3)
- Office Procedures -- General, 1964-1966 (Box 3)
- Office Procedures -- Grant Actions, 1951-1965 (Box 3)
- Office Procedures -- Grant Actions, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
- International Training and Research (ITR) -- Administrative Reorganization -- Neremco Services, Inc., 1963 (Box 3)
- Secretary's Report on Grant Actions -- Fiscal 1957 (Box 3)
- Unpaid Grants and Unused Appropriations as of Dec 31, 1964 and May 31, 1965 -- Memoranda to and from Mr. Heald, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
- Procedures Manual (1/2), 1958-1964 (Box 3)
- Procedures Manual (2/2), 1958-1964 (Box 3)
- Program Planning, 1951-1967
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for Area One, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Program Planning for International Training and Research (ITR), 1958 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, May 1953 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, June 1953 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, Sep 16, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, Nov 24, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, May 21-22, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, Oct 29-30, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, Dec 17-18, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, Mar 4-5, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, May 26-28, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, Sep 30, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, Nov 16, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, Dec 8, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, Dec 9-10, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, Feb 10, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, Mar 8-9, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, Apr 17, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, May 11, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, Jun 18, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting, Jun 18-19, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, Jul 13, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, Sep 1956 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, Dec 6-8, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings -- Memoranda, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, Jan 15, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Trustees and Executive Committee Meetings, Mar 21-22, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, May 9, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Trustees and Executive Committee Meetings, Jun 20-22, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Trustees and Executive Committee Meetings, Sep 1957 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, Nov 15, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, Dec 12-14, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, Mar 20-22, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, May 16, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, Jun 19-21, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee and Trustees Meetings, Sep 25-27, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Training and Research, Reports, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Report -- "Some Conclusions concerining Ford Fellowship Program", Jan 20, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Report -- "Recommendations on the 1955-56 Fellowship Programs", Jan 21, 1955 (Box 4)
  - International Training and Research -- Reports, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Training and Research -- Status Reports, 1955-1961 (Box 4)
  - International Training and Research -- Reports, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Division of Overseas Activities -- Budget Material, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Merillat -- International Training and Research (ITR) Budget, 1956-1958 (Box 4)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee Only, Oct 26, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee and Full Board, Dec 7-8, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Trustees and Executive Committee Meetings (without ITR Docket Items), 1962 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee and Full Board, Mar 22-23, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee, May 4, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee and Full Board, Jun 21-22, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Sep 27-28, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Executive Committee (cancelled), Oct 26, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Dec 13-14, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, Feb 8, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Mar 28-29, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting -- Attachments, Mar 28-29, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Jun 20-21, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Sep 26-27, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Dec 12-13, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee, Feb 3, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Apr 2-3, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Jun 18-19, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Sep 24-25, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Dec 10-11, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Program Planning Budget Reports 1962, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program Planning Budget, 1962 (Box 5)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program Planning Budgets for Fiscal 1963-1965, Jul 20, 1962 (Box 5)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Planning Budget Request for Fiscal 1963-1965, Sep 1962 (Box 5)
  - Program Planning Budget Reports, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
  - Program Planning Budget Reports, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, Mar 25-26, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, Jun 1965 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, Sep 30-Oct 1, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, Dec 9-10, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, Mar 14-15, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, Jun 23-24, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, Sep 28-29, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Program Planning Budget Reports, Dec 1964-Sep 1965 (Box 6)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program Planning Budget FY 1964-1966, Apr 22, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Program Planning FY 1965-1967 (Box 6)
- Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) / Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR), 1952-1957 (Box 7)
  - Establishment of Board on Overseas Training and Research (BOTR), 1952 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, Mar 18, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Minutes of Meetings and other reports, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, May 22, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, Jun 18, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, Sep 17, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, Nov 13, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, May 5, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, Sep 15, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, Nov 18, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR) Meeting, Mar 31, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Board of Overseas Training and Research (BOTR), Minutes of Meetings and Other Reports, 1953-1954 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) Meeting, Oct 21, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) - General Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) Meeting, Apr 29, 1955 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) Meeting, Dec 20, 1955 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) - General Correspondence, 1956 (Box 7)
  - Interim Report to Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR), Jun 1956 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) Letter, Jul 1956 (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on International Training and Research (ACITR) - General Correspondence, 1957 (Box 7)
- Program Planning, Consultants, 1959-1967 (Box 8)
  - Secretary's Reports on Ford Foundation Grants, 1959-1964 (Box 8)
  - Grants Index, [1959] (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Program Evaluation 1951-1961 and Statement of Current Objectives and Policies, 1961-1962 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Administrative Budget FY 1963-1967 (Box 8)
  - Manpower Planning and Development, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultant -- Professor Donald Adams, Jun 25, 1965 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultants -- General File, 1953-1963 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultant -- Robert F. Byrnes, 1958 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultant -- Neal Gross, 1959-1960 (Box 8)
  - International Training and Research (ITR), Consultant -- Melville Ruggles (Box 8)